Finding Aid for Euline McCorkle Taratsas Papers 1951-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Euline McCorkle Taratsas Papers 1951-2001 1972-1993
Taratsas, Euline McCorkle, 1936-2001.
A polio survivor, Taratsas worked on behalf of people with disabilities and contributed to many advocacy organizations, particularly the National Association for the Physically Handicapped, the Physically Impaired Association of Michigan, and the Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living. Biographical/personal materials includes interview, correspondence, and photographs; files relating to her organizational affiliations; subject files pertaining to her advocacy work; and collected scrapbooks of photographs and memorabilia of polio survivors at University Hospital of the University of Michigan, 1951-1964.
0299, Aa/2; Ac
1.0 linear feet
1 oversize folders
1 oversize boxes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Evelyn King (Donor no. 9175 ), February 2002 and Linda Brown (Donor no. 9321 ), May 2003.
The collection is open for research.
Euline McCorkle, or "Corki," was born on November 26, 1936 in Decaturville, Tennessee. She contracted polio after completing the third grade and spent seven months on the critical list in a hospital in Memphis, Tennessee. She was completely paralyzed during this period and required the use of an iron lung. After seven months, continual respiratory support was no longer necessary and she was transferred to the Crippled Children's School in Memphis, where she received her fourth and fifth grade training. She returned to her home near Memphis where she then completed her sixth grade while bedridden via a local homebound schooling program. At the age of twelve, both of her parents died in an automobile accident, and both she and her sister were sent to Ypsilanti, Michigan to live with an older brother and his wife.
For a time, McCorkle was a patient in the children's division at University Hospital and studied to a limited extent at the hospital school. She was then moved to Mary Free Bed, in Grand Rapids, Michigan. Through rehabilitation, she was soon able to sit upright in a wheelchair for short periods of time. She returned to the Ann Arbor area and completed her seventh grade work through the homebound program. She was enrolled in a rehabilitation program at the School for the Handicapped in Farmington, Michigan, where she regained some use of her hands and completed her eighth grade work. Shortly after her transfer to the Ann Arbor Convalescent Home, she contracted pneumonia in both lungs and returned to the University Hospital, where she again required substantial respiratory support.
After recovery she returned home and began the homebound program associated with Ann Arbor High School. For one semester in tenth grade, Taratsas attended the high school in a wheelchair. She soon contracted pneumonia again and resumed homebound instruction. She received her high school diploma in June 1962 with high honors from Willow Run High School. In subsequent terms, she earned credits from the University of Michigan, Eastern Michigan and Michigan State in classes related to human services and graduated from Cleary College in Ann Arbor with a degree in business administration.
McCorkle was firmly committed to the advocacy needs of people with disabilities, and contributed to many different organizations in multiple areas, on a local, state and national level. She was the area and chapter president of the National Association of the Physically Handicapped, a charter member of Physically Impaired Association of Michigan, and one of the founders of the Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living. Taratsas sat on the Governors Commission of barrier free design and the Presidents Task Force on barrier free design, on the Governors Task Force for Vocational Rehabilitation and the board for the Ann Arbor Transportation Authority. She was the recipient of many awards and recognized for her role as an advocate, from the 1960s to the 1990s.
Taratsas was also an active member of the First Baptist Church of Ann Arbor. On August 26, 1978, she married James Taratsas and also shared custody of James's young son. She died of breast cancer on September 26, 2001.
The Euline McCorkle Taratsas Papers document her active role in the disability rights movement, on a local, regional and national level. The papers are organized into three series: Biographical/Personal, Advocacy for People with Disabilities, and Scrapbooks and Collected Materials.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living.; National Association of the Physically Handicapped.; Physically Impaired Association of Michigan.; People with disabilities--Michigan.; People with disabilities--Services for--Michigan.; Poliomyelitis--Patients.; Taratsas, Euline McCorkle, 1936-2001.; Women with disabilities--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Breathing apparatus.; Children--Health and welfare--Michigan.; Medical equipment and supplies.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; People with disabilities--Michigan.; Taratsas, Euline McCorkle, 1936-2001.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.
Wheelchairs.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Posters.
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal series consist newspaper clippings, a vita, scrapbooks, correspondence, and photographs. Several interviews with Taratsas provide a wealth of biographical information as does a transcription of an award speech, her vita, and the many newspaper articles about Taratsas.
  - Biographical materials, newspaper clippings 1955-1977 (Box 1)
  - Biographical materials, clippings and vita undated, 1962-2002 (Box 1)
  - Biographical materials, medical files and information undated, 1962-2002 (Box 1)
  - Personal memorabilia 1962-1985 (Box 1)
  - Interview, "I Count My Abilities, Not My Disabilities" July 3, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Post-polio syndrome clippings and resources undated, 1985-1993 (Box 1)
  - Polio field trials signed by Jonas Salk 1955-1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1962-1976 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1979-1996 (Box 1)
  - Term Paper by Frederick Petzinger on NAPH Chapter 76 and Euline Taratsas 1985 (Box 1)
  - Unedited Transcript of Laurie Thomas Interview with Euline McCorkle Taratsas 1998 (Box 1)
  - Proud Voices: An Oral History of the Disability Rights Movement by Lauren Thomas, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Personal photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Personal photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs of event with Governor, undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph, Euline McCorkle in office, undated (Box 1)
- Advocacy for People with Disabilities
  The Advocacy for People with Disabilities series is further segmented into three subseries, Organizations and Events, Topical, and Regional. The Organization and Events subseries contain papers, newsletters, clippings, correspondence, notes, pamphlets and committee notes for several organizations in which Taratsas remained a vital member. The Topical sub-series contain clippings, newsletters, memoranda, correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, judgments, letters and factsheets on topics which she was committed to which concerned more than one institution. The Regional subseries contains correspondence, township proclamations and certificates, proclamations, newsletters, and committee reports on which Taratsas served as a local citizen and advocate.
  - Organizations and Events
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped 1959-1980 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped Barrier Free Design Committee speeches and correspondence 1974-1981 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped publication, Ypsilanti Chapter Meeting Minutes 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped undated, 1980-1992 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped correspondence 1984-1988 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped, Michigan Area Convention 1987 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped publication, "Newsline," 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the Physically Handicapped, Michigan Area Council Meeting Minutes 1987-1996 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living 1972-1995 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living, Grant Applications and Proposals 1978 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living, Staff Meeting Minutes and Notes 1978 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living, Certificates and Pamphlets 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living, correspondence 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living, CIL Task Force Minutes 1979 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living, Cassette Tape of AACIL Dinner on November 24, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Center for Independent Living poster, "Don't Cramp My Style" (Box 1)
      in oversize folder
    - Physically Impaired Association of Michigan 1975-1985 (Box 1)
    - State of Michigan, Vocational Rehabilitation Service undated, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Handicapper Network 1988-2000 (Box 1)
    - White Conference on Handicapped Individuals undated, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Topical
    - Barrier-Free undated, 1974-1993 (Box 1)
    - Health Care undated, 1975-1992 (Box 1)
    - Legal undated, 1976-1990 (Box 1)
    - Legislation undated, 1972-1991 (Box 1)
    - Employment undated, 1962-1983 (Box 1)
  - Regional
    - Ypsilanti 1972-1990 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor 1979-1984 (Box 1)
    - Detroit undated, 1979 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks and Collected Materials
  Several of the scrapbooks in the Scrapbooks and Collected Materials series were not initially created by Taratsas but were given to her to aid her in her research of Post-polio and its effects. Patrons interested in researching the University of Michigan Respirator Center, the University Hospital Children's Rehabilitation Service or Camp Aowakiya of Jackson Michigan will find a great deal of photographs, leaflets and programs in these scrapbooks.
  - University of Michigan Respirator Center Scrapbook 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Respirator Center Scrapbook 1956-1960 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Respirator Center Scrapbook, Loose photographs, 1954-1960 (Box 1)
  - Post-Polio Survivors Hospital Scrapbook 1954-1958 (Box 1)
  - Post-Polio Survivors Hospital Scrapbook, Loose photographs, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
  - University Hospital Scrapbook 1951-1953 (Box 2)
  - University Hospital Scrapbook 1953 (Box 2)
  - University Hospital Scrapbook, loose photographs (Box 2)
  - Camp Aowakiya Scrapbook, Jackson Michigan 1954-1957 (Box 2)
  - Camp Aowakiya Scrapbook, Jackson Michigan 1957-1964 (Box 2)
  - Camp Aowakiya Scrapbook, Jackson Michigan, loose items (Box 2)
  - University Hospital Children's Rehabilitation Service "Penthouse" Scrapbook 1960-1962 (Box 2)
  - University Hospital Children's Rehabilitation Service "Penthouse" Scrapbook, loose photographs (Box 2)